1949年8月17日凌晨3点09分，412号客运列车正驶近日本的松川村
August 17th, 1949, 3.09 a.m. Passenger train 412 is approaching the village of Matsukawa, Japan.
此前，这趟在东北本线上的旅途尚算平稳，但一场灾难已在60秒之外悄然逼近
So far, the journey on the Tohoku mainline has gone smoothly, but disaster is only 60 seconds away.
在过去的两个月里，日本一直被铁路恐怖主义的阴云所笼罩
For the last two months, Japan has been inflamed with railroad terrorism.
七月，日本国有铁道总裁遭人绑架并被火车碾压身亡
In July, the president of the Japanese National Railway Authority was kidnapped and run over with a train.
请参见“下山事件”，死者为日本国有铁道第一任总裁下山定则
数日后，又一列火车遭人蓄意破坏
Days later, someone tampered with another train,
失控冲入站台，致使六人丧生
causing it to lose control and crash into a platform, killing six.
而在此地，有人拆除了连接两段铁轨的部件，并将铁轨移开了数英尺之远
And here, someone has removed pieces connecting two portions of the track and shifted the rails several feet apart.
此为『松川事件』，与同年度发生之下山事件及三鹰事件，并称为『国铁三大谜案』
灾难，仅在30秒之外
Disaster is only 30 seconds away.
所有这些袭击的动机都昭然若揭
The motive for all these attacks is obvious.
自七月以来，超过十万名铁路工人遭到解雇
Since July, over 100,000 railroad workers have been fired.
公私部门合计，逾两百万人失去工作
Between the public and private sector, over 2 million have lost their jobs,
而日本经济在二战的重创下仍未恢复
while Japan's economy remains shattered by the Second World War.
绝望情绪蔓延，共产党人的势力则在该国强大的工会中日益壮大
Despair is widespread, and communists have been growing in power throughout the country's powerful trade unions.
他们是七月里首当其冲被解雇的群体
They were the first to lose their jobs in July.
而现在，灾难已然……
And now, disaster is only.
412号列车发生了毁灭性的出轨事故
Train 412 derails catastrophically.
两人当场死亡
Two men are killed instantly.
分别是49岁的司机石田正造和27岁的司炉工伊藤敏一
49-year-old engineer Ishida Shozo and 27-year-old fireman Ito Toshiiichi.
我在日文维基百科并未查询到死者名称，询问AI后得到该三人名称，如有错误请指正
23岁的助理司机茂木正市则在咽下最后一口气前，对列车长喘息着说出
The assistant engineer, 23-year-old Mogi Masaichi, lives just long enough to gasp to the train's conductor.
“列车は破坏された”
列车遭到了蓄意破坏
The train was sabotaged.
但究竟是谁所为？
But who did it?
二十名共产党人很快被指控并定了罪
Twenty communists were quickly charged and convicted.
他们的动机，如我所言，显而易见
Their motive, like I said, was obvious.
但他们为何会有动机？
But why did they have a motive?
为何如此多的人在短时间内被解雇？
Why were so many people fired so quickly?
又为何共产党人最先遭殃？
And why were communists the first to go?
这并非日本自行决定的政策
It wasn't a policy the Japanese had decided on.
而是由战后占领该国的美国当局所强加的
Instead, it was imposed by American authorities who had occupied the nation since the end of the war.
官方说法是，他们此举旨在帮助日本从一个好战的帝国主义国家
Officially, they were there to help Japan transition from a bellicose imperial state
过渡为和平的德谟克拉西国家
into a pacifist democracy.
占领之初，他们确实是这么做的
And when the occupation began, that's what they did.
但在过去一年里，这一使命逐渐淡化
But over the last year, that mission faded into the background.
如今，美国意图将战犯从监狱中释放，转而关押共产党人
Now, America was intent on releasing war criminals from prison, locking up communists instead,
并让日本的战时领导人重掌大权
and returning Japan's wartime leaders to power,
即便这意味着要动用中情局来资助他们的政治活动
even if it meant using the CIA to fund their political campaigns.
于是共产党人予以反击，至少，当时人人都是这么认为的
So the communists struck back. At least, that's what everyone thought.
然而，历经十四年的审判与重审
Except, after 14 years of trials and retrials,
这二十名被告最终被东京高等法院宣告无罪
those 20 individuals were ultimately acquitted by the Tokyo High Court.
整件事就是一场骗局
The whole thing was a sham.
但如果不是他们干的，那还有谁有动机？
But if they didn't do it, who else had a motive?
根据被告们的说法，他们是遭人陷害
According to the accused, they were set up,
为美国当局的内部阴谋背了黑锅
framed for an inside job by the American authorities,
美国当局企图将共产党人描绘成恐怖分子
who sought to paint communists as terrorists,
以此来验证并加速其政策转向，从包容性德谟克拉西转向反共主义
to validate and accelerate their pivot away from an inclusive democracy and toward anti-communism.
谁是松川事件中破坏铁轨的真凶，这个问题触及了日本战后历史的核心
The question of who really sabotaged the tracks at Matsukawa is one that goes to the heart of Japan's post-war history.
即它如何演变成我们今天所知的国家
How it became the nation we know today.
这是一个黑暗的故事，讲述了一项理想主义的使命
And it's a dark story of how an idealistic mission
如何演变为一场为达美国政治目的而不择手段的冷酷阴谋
transformed into a cynical plot to bend Japanese politics to American ends,
无论代价为何
whatever the cost.
贿赂
Bribery.
盗窃
Theft.
间谍活动
Espionage.
甚至一位首相也被中情局收买
Even a prime minister on the CIA payroll.
1949年的日本，是伤痕背后的故事
Japan 1949 is the story behind the scars.
是这个国家德谟克拉西制度中那些从未真正愈合的深层创伤
The deep wounds in the country's democracy that have never truly healed.
松川事件的故事，是一场德谟克拉西的理想主义与冷酷的反共主义之间的较量
The story of Matsukawa is the story of a battle between democratic idealism and cynical anti-communism.
而这个故事始于此物
And that story begins with this.
《日本国宪法》
The Constitution of Japan.
证物甲
Exhibit A.
理想主义者最伟大的成就
The Idealist's Greatest Achievement.
它于1946年由日本国会，即立法机构通过，但并非由他们撰写
It was adopted in 1946 by the Japanese Diet, or legislature, but it was not written by them.
相反，它是由二战后占领日本的美国人起草的
Instead, it was drafted by the Americans who, after World War II, occupied Japan.
其中包括政治学家，法律学者和历史学家
Political scientists, legal scholars, and historians.
当然还有占领军最高司令官，道格拉斯·麦克阿瑟，这位理想主义的总指挥
And the occupation's supreme commander, Douglas MacArthur, the idealist-in-chief.
这部宪法充满了理想主义色彩
The Constitution exudes idealism.
第九条【放弃战争，否认军备及交战权】
Article 9 renounces war forever,
鉴于日本刚发动了一场导致亚洲三千万人丧生的冲突，这是一个至关重要的条款
a vital condition given Japan has recently started a conflict that killed 30 million people throughout Asia.
第十一条至第四十条则保障了个人权利
Articles 11 through 40 enshrine individual rights,
包括言论自由，政治参与和宗教自由等经典权利
including the classics like freedom of speech, political participation, and religion.
但也包含了一些美国宪法所没有的权利
But also some absent from the American Constitution,
如平等的教育权，学术自由，思想自由
like rights to equal education, academic freedom, freedom of thought,
隐私权，以及对松川事件至关重要的，工人组织和集体谈判的自由
privacy, and, crucially for the Matsukawa case, freedom of workers to organize and bargain collectively.
本着同样的理想主义精神
In the same spirit of idealism,
麦克阿瑟作为占领军统帅的第一个行动并非惩罚，而是解放
MacArthur's very first act as head of the occupation was not to punish, but to liberate.
他释放了日本所有的2500名政治犯，其中包括许多共产党领导人
Freeing all of Japan's 2,500 political prisoners, including many leading communists.
与此同时，他对200名日本战时领导人采取了截然相反的措施
At the same time, he gave 200 of Japan's wartime leaders the opposite treatment.
麦克阿瑟认为他们对挑起战争负有最大责任
Deeming them most responsible for instigating the war,
将他们定为甲级战犯
MacArthur labeled them Class A war criminals,
永远禁止他们担任公职或政府雇员
banished them forever from public office or government employment,
并将其中许多人投入监狱，等待罪行审判
and imprisoned many of them to await trial for their crimes.
理想主义正高歌猛进
Idealism was on the march,
但松川的悲剧已在酝酿之中，因为这种理想主义存在盲点
but the tragedy at Matsukawa was brewing already, because that idealism had blind spots.
我们热衷于讲述这类故事
This is the kind of story we love telling,
对一个谜团进行抽丝剥茧的调查
the slow-burn investigation of a mystery that,
层层揭开之后，一个关乎德谟克拉西真谛的故事便浮出水面
as you peel back layer by layer, reveals a story that matters to democracy.
前方广告，请空降7:51
现在，回到日本
Now, back to Japan.
有了宪法，麦克阿瑟的理想主义似乎有了一个强有力的开端
With the Constitution, MacArthur's idealism seemed to be off to a strong start.
但松川的悲剧已在酝酿之中，因为这种理想主义存在盲点
But the tragedy at Matsukawa was already in the making, because that idealism had blind spots.
因为麦克阿瑟的理想主义并未止步于政治
Because MacArthur's idealism didn't stop at politics.
他还着手建立一个德谟克拉西的经济
He also set about building a democratic economy,
这意味着要解散财阀，即大型企业集团，并在总体上分散经济权力
which meant dismantling the zaibatsu, or megacorporations, and generally deconcentrating economic power.
然而，在这个饱受战争摧残的国家，这些目标中
Conspicuously missing from these objectives in the war-shattered country, however,
却明显缺失了经济增长这一项
was economic growth.
于是我们来到证物乙
And so we land at Exhibit B,
公告栏，这是工人阶级之间主要的交流方式
the Bulletin Board, the primary means of communication amongst the working class.
在日本各地，随着新获释的党员重建其势力
All over Japan, advertisements for communist gatherings appeared on these boards
共产党集会的广告出现在这些公告栏上
as newly released party members rebuilt their power.
与此同时，麦克阿瑟的德谟克拉西经济陷入停滞
At the same time, MacArthur's democratic economy froze.
增长停滞不前，失业率激增
Growth went flat, and unemployment exploded.
反过来，对共产党人的支持日益增长
In turn, support for the communists grew,
将他们推上了日本受宪法保障的劳工团体的领导岗位
catapulting them into leadership roles in Japan's constitutionally empowered labor groups,
其中包括国铁劳动组合
including the National Railway Workers Union.
一位前劳工团体主席回忆道
One former president of a labor group recalled,
“在占领初期，麦克阿瑟不仅容忍
MacArthur, in the early stages of the occupation, didn't merely tolerate,
甚至欢迎共产党人参与中央及地方劳动关系委员会等重要机构”
but welcomed the participation of communists in such important bodies as the central and local labor relations commissions.
这当然只是麦克阿瑟和占领当局德谟克拉西理想主义的延伸
It was, of course, merely an extension of MacArthur's and the occupation's democratic idealism.
每个人都有权参与并表达自己的信念
Everyone had a right to participate and express their beliefs.
但在麦克阿瑟的眼皮底下，新的权力中心正在形成
But new centers of power were developing under MacArthur's nose,
尤其是占领军的秘密军事情报单位，G-2
particularly the occupation's secretive military intelligence unit, G-2,
由麦克阿瑟的亲信查尔斯·威洛比少将领导
headed by MacArthur's close confidant, Major General Charles Willoughby,
此人为德美混血，由于姓Adolf且极度反共而被冠以『小希特勒』之名
他对麦克阿瑟理想主义的智慧愈发持怀疑态度
who was increasingly skeptical about the wisdom of MacArthur's idealism.
在威洛比看来，巨大的威胁并非是刚引发战争的军国主义民族主义的复苏
To Willoughby, the great threat wasn't a resurgence of the militant nationalism that had just caused the war
如麦克阿瑟所担心的那样
as MacArthur feared,
而是共产主义
it was communism.
于是威洛比利用G-2的保密性，绕过麦克阿瑟
So Willoughby exploited G-2's secrecy, went behind MacArthur's back,
开始在日本建立一个反共间谍网络
and began building an anti-communist spy network in Japan.
为此，威洛比需要专业知识，也需要资金
To do that, Willoughby needed expertise, and he needed money.
他需要儿玉誉士夫
He needed Kodama Yoshio.
儿玉誉士夫，日本右翼运动家，自称CIA特工，兼任暴力团稻川会顾问
于第二次世界大战时在上海担任“儿玉机关”领导人，战后于朝鲜战争时期在美国中央情报局掩护下致富
捐资成立自民党，为日本战后到1970年代黑社会领袖
在洛克希德政治献金事件与首相田中角荣皆被求刑。
在中国，儿玉不仅是日本侵华和占领期间至关重要的情报官员——
In China, Kodama hadn't just been a vital intelligence officer in the Japanese invasion and occupation,
那场战争导致了数千万人死亡
which killed tens of millions.
他还窃取了价值1.75亿美元的中国黄金和钻石
He'd actually made off with $175 million worth of stolen Chinese gold and diamonds.
他正是G-2所需要的那种人
He was exactly the sort of man G-2 needed,
但他也正是被麦克阿瑟关押并贴上甲级战犯标签的那种人
but he was also exactly the sort of man MacArthur locked up and branded a Class A war criminal.
不过到了1948年，麦克阿瑟脚下的土地正在发生变化
But by 1948, the ground was shifting beneath MacArthur's feet.
共产党人正在扭转解放战争的局势
Communists were turning the tide in China's civil war,
而且有传言称，苏联支持的对朝鲜的入侵即将来临
and rumors swirled that a Soviet-backed invasion of Korea was on the horizon.
于是，我们来到了松川事件的前夜
And so, we arrive at the doorstep of the Matsukawa incident,
证物丙，《赖德信函》
Exhibit C, the Ryder letter.
由麦克阿瑟的一位下属查尔斯·赖德将军于1948年10月撰写
Penned by one of MacArthur's subordinates, General Charles Ryder, in October 1948,
这无异于一场针对麦克阿瑟理想主义的叛变
it's nothing less than a mutiny against MacArthur's idealism.
“一方面，我们有义务在处理共产主义问题时，以美国政府的最佳利益行事”
On the one hand, we find ourselves bound to act in the best interests of the United States government in handling the communist problem.
“而另一方面，我们作为占领军
And on the other hand, we, as an occupying force,
又致力于在日本赞助一种德谟克拉西形式的政府”
are committed to the sponsorship of a democratic form of government in Japan.
“那么，我们能否让日本成为一块共产主义可以蓬勃发展的绿洲？”
Can we then maintain Japan as an oasis in which communism may flourish?
“这与美国政府的既定立场直接相悖”
In direct opposition to the stated position of the United States government?
“答案是断然的‘不行’！”
The answer is an emphatic no.
换言之，根据赖德的说法
In other words, according to Ryder,
是时候让德谟克拉西为国家安全和反共主义让路了
it was time for democracy to take a back seat to national security and anti-communism.
华盛顿方面也表示同意
And Washington agreed.
同年，美国冷战战略的设计师乔治·凯南
That same year, George Kennan, the architect of America's Cold War strategy,
从华盛顿前往东京，向麦克阿瑟宣读训令
traveled from Washington to Tokyo to read MacArthur the Riot Act.
他的要求与赖德的批评意见一致
His demands were in line with Ryder's criticism.
结束雄心勃勃的经济实验
End the ambitious economic experiment.
削弱共产党人的影响力
Reduce the influence of the communists.
并开始从监狱释放甲级战犯
And begin releasing class A war criminals from prison.
松川事件此刻已不可避免
Matsukawa was now inevitable.
到十二月，儿玉誉士夫重获自由
By December, Kurama Yoshio was a free man.
他很快便与威洛比的G-2合作
And he was soon working with Willoughby's G-2
从中国走私贵金属，这是儿玉的专长
to smuggle precious metals out of China, Kurama's specialty,
为“高松计划”提供资金
to fund the Takamatsu Plan,
这是一份旨在建立庞大且集权的日本情报行动
a blueprint for a vast and centralized Japanese intelligence operation
以在国内外对抗共产主义的蓝图
to fight communism at home and abroad.
与此同时，1949年2月，共和党银行家约瑟夫·道奇抵达日本
Meanwhile, in February 1949, Joseph Dodge, a Republican bank president, arrived in Japan.
明面上，他是杜鲁门总统派来担任麦克阿瑟财务顾问的
Officially, he was sent by President Truman as a financial advisor to MacArthur.
实际上，他是来掌管大局并攻击日本共产党权力的根源——
In reality, he was there to take charge and attack the root of communist power in Japan,
即麦克阿瑟那停滞不前的德谟克拉西经济的
MacArthur's stagnant, democratic economy.
道奇向吉田首相传达的信息很明确
Dodge's message to Prime Minister Yoshida was clear.
他必须通过一份平衡预算，而那意味着要大幅削减政府开支
He would have to pass a balanced budget, and that meant slashing government spending.
经过数月的争论，吉田最终妥协
It took months of wrangling before Yoshida finally caved,
1949年4月，日本国会通过了该预算
but in April 1949, Japan's Diet passed the budget.
现在，可怕的部分来了
Now, the scary part.
政府必须解雇约30%的员工
The government had to fire about 30% of its employees.
仅日本国有铁道一家，就必须裁掉十万个工作岗位
The Japanese National Railway Authority, or JNR, alone had to shed 100,000 jobs.
7月1日，各铁路分局收到了国铁总裁下山定则从东京发来的命令
On July 1st, each railroad division received orders from JNR President Shimoyama Sadanori in Tokyo
命令中包含了将被解雇，即“首切り”的人数，字面意思为“砍头”
with the numbers to be fired, or kubikiri, translated literally, decapitated.
官方说法是，解雇将根据效率和资历来决定
Officially, the firings were to be decided according to efficiency and seniority.
但当7月4日裁员开始时，有影响力的共产党人却是最先被“砍头”的一批
But influential communists were among the first to figuratively lose their heads when the layoffs began on July 4th.
次日，国铁总裁下山本人则遭遇了更为字面意义上的“首切り”
The next day, JNR President Shimoyama suffered a more literal kubikiri.
他的尸体碎块散落在东京的铁轨周围，被一列火车碾过
He was found in pieces, scattered around railroad tracks in Tokyo, run over by a train.
官方尸检报告认定，由于惨烈的现场血迹极少
The official autopsy determined, on account of the minimal blood at the gruesome scene,
下山在被人陈尸于铁轨上之前，便已经死亡了一段时间
that Shimoyama had been dead for some time, before someone laid his body on the tracks.
尽管他遭谋杀，7月14日，第二轮也是最后一轮的“首切り”还是按计划进行
Despite his murder, though, on July 14th, the second and final round of kubikiri carried on as planned.
次日，一列火车冲入郊区的三鹰站，导致六名候车乘客死亡
The next day, a train careened into the suburban Mitaka station, killing six waiting passengers.
它的控制器被人绑住，从而引发了事故
Its controls had been tied down, causing the crash.
而8月17日，在远离东京的松川附近，412号客运列车出轨，三人遇难
And on August 17th, far from Tokyo, passenger train 412 derailed near Matsukawa, killing three.
在这三起袭击中，当局都迅速将矛头指向了铁路工会中的共产党人
In all three attacks, authorities quickly blamed communists in the railroad labor unions.
松川事件中怀疑的理由是显而易见的
The cause for suspicion in the Matsukawa case is obvious.
其一，铁路工人，铁路恐怖主义，把这两点联系起来看
For one, railroad workers, railroad terrorism, connect the dots.
但更重要的是，共产党工人们有明确的动机和手段
But more importantly, the communist workers had clear motive and means.
就动机而言，十万名铁路员工刚刚被解雇
As for motive, 100,000 railway employees had just been laid off.
而唯一比大规模裁员更让共产党人愤怒的是
And the only thing that angers communists more than mass layoffs are
专门针对共产党人的大规模裁员
mass layoffs that especially target communists.
至于手段，破坏铁路并非易事
As for means, railroad sabotage isn't an easy business.
它需要重型工具，而在战后日本的农村地区并不容易获得
It requires heavy-duty tools not readily accessible in post-war rural Japan.
除非你碰巧在铁路维修部门工作
Unless you happen to work in railroad maintenance.
但即使有工具，一个破坏者也无法单独完成
But even with the tools, a lone saboteur couldn't manage it.
这必然是一场阴谋
But this had to be a conspiracy.
而没有什么比共产党人这个词更能与阴谋联系在一起了
And nothing rhymes with conspiracy like communists.
然而，尽管动机和手段都很明确，唯一的物证却只是一两件工具
Despite the clear motive and means, however, the only physical evidence was a couple of tools,
显然是从附近一个国铁铁路维修补给棚里偷来的
apparently stolen from a nearby JNR rail maintenance supply shed.
但那个棚子是被人闯入的
But the shed was broken into,
所以这并不能证明阴谋涉及有权进入的工人
so that didn't actually prove the conspiracy involved workers with access to it.
警方所掌握的，是供词
What the police did have were confessions.
他们在九月逮捕了一名前铁路维修工，19岁的赤间胜美
They picked up a former rail maintenance worker, 19-year-old Akama Katsumi, in September.
十天后，赤间招供，并指认松川的四名共产党工会成员为主谋
Ten days later, Akama confessed and named four communist union members in Matsukawa as the ringleaders.
其中一人随后也做了同样的事，又指认了另外几名共产党同伙，如此循环
One of them then did the same, naming a handful more communist accomplices, and so on, until
直到警方逮捕了20名共产党人
the police had 20 communists under arrest.
然而，有几个问题
Except there were a few problems.
其一，随着时间推移和新证据的出现，警方邀请嫌疑人修改他们详细的供词
For one, as time went on and new evidence arose, police invited their suspects to revise their
以使其与事实保持一致
detailed confessions to remain consistent with the facts.
可靠的证据就这样化为乌有
So much for reliable evidence.
其二，后来披露的警方内部文件显示，警方几乎只关注日本铁路工会的成员
For another, internal police documents later revealed that police focused almost exclusively on members of Japan's railroad union,
而忽略了其他可能的嫌疑人
ignoring other possible suspects.
最后，并非所有20名嫌疑人都是共产党人
And finally, not all 20 suspects were communist.
事实上，有一个不是
In fact, one wasn't.
就是那个最初供出几名共产党人，从而引发整个事件的人
The one who kicked it all off by fingering a handful of communists in the first place.
少年赤间胜美
Teenager Akama Katsumi.
而他之所以招供
And he only confessed
是在警方威胁要杀死他
after police threatened to kill him,
并告诉他一些共产党人已经指责他之后，还说他应该报复他们
and told him some communists had already blamed him, and that he should get even with them.
而这些还只是拙劣警务工作的冰山一角
And those are just the highlights of the shoddy police work.
我的意思是，这个兔子洞深不见底
I mean, this rabbit hole is deep.
如果你想了解更多，请查看我们在Patreon和Nebula上的播客
If you want more, check out our podcast on Patreon and Nebula.
但这些已经足够我们开始探讨另一种理论了
But that's enough to get us set up and look at the alternative theory.
即这是美国政府策划的一场栽赃陷害
That this was a frame-up job by the American government.
首先，其动机与共产党人一样昭然若揭
For one, the motive is equally obvious as the communists.
威洛比的G-2只有一个任务，即阻碍共产主义的发展
Willoughby's G-2 had one mission, disrupt the growth of communism.
我们知道，像儿玉这样的日本特工
We know that Japanese agents like Kodama
参与了走私等非法活动，且常常与美国同行合作
were engaged in shady activity like smuggling, often alongside American counterparts.
不难想象需要一次假旗行动
It isn't a stretch to imagine a false flag, and
而还有什么比松川事件更好的方式呢
what better way to do that than the Matsukawa incident?
我的意思是，铁路工人，铁路恐怖主义，把这两点联系起来看
I mean, railroad workers, railroad terrorism, connect the dots.
在那些裁员之后，除了他们，还有谁会受到指责？
And in the aftermath of those layoffs, who else would anyone blame?
不过，当时几乎没人知道G-2的存在
Back then, though, almost nobody knew about G-2.
那时，人们一无所知
Back then, nobody knew a thing.
此案在法庭上耗时14年，历经重审、上诉再重审，是有原因的
There's a reason the case spent 14 years in court, in retrial after appeal after retrial,
直到东京高等法院最终宣布被告无罪
until the Tokyo High Court finally declared the defendants not guilty.
这是一起发生在农村的调查，基本上没有任何物证可循
It was a rural investigation, with basically zero physical evidence to go off of.
因此，我们可能永远无法确切知道是谁在松川破坏了铁轨
As a result, we'll likely never know who sabotaged the tracks at Matsukawa.
但今天，我们确实知道一些他们当时所不知道的事情
But today, we do know some things they didn't know then.
我们知道G-2当时正在积蓄力量，执行着远比这复杂得多的秘密行动
We know that G-2 was building its strength, carrying out clandestine acts far more complex than this,
比如儿玉的走私阴谋
like Kodama's smuggling plot.
而且我们知道，像威洛比这样的当代犬儒主义者
And we know the cynics like Willoughby
再也找不到比这更好的借口，来为放弃日本的德谟克拉西实验
couldn't have asked for a better excuse to justify abandoning Japan's democratic experiment
并转向反共主义提供正当理由了
and pivoting to anti-communism.
他们声称，而且大多数人也相信
Matsukawa, they argued, and most believed,
松川事件是麦克阿瑟理想主义项目的最终结局和最严厉的控诉
was the culmination and ultimate indictment of MacArthur's idealistic project.
宽容，自由，企业反垄断，工人权力
Toleration, freedom, corporate trust-busting, worker power.
这些全都是错误，它们助长了共产主义并激发了恐怖主义
They were all mistakes which bolstered communism and inspired terrorism.
而今天，多亏了文件被缓慢解密
And today, thanks to the slow declassification of documents,
我们知道了后来发生了什么
we know what happened next.
我们知道，在1949年，一切都改变了
We know that in 1949, everything changed.
简而言之，理想主义者失败了，犬儒主义者接管了局面
In short, the idealists lost, and the cynics took charge,
他们着手一项秘密计划，在日本建立反共政治，不惜任何代价
undertaking a secret project to build anti-communist politics in Japan, whatever the cost.
这是麦克阿瑟在1950年6月写给吉田首相的一封信
This is a letter from MacArthur to Prime Minister Yoshida from June 1950,
那时对被控破坏者的审判甚至还未结束
before the trial of the accused saboteurs had even wrapped.
麦克阿瑟命令他
MacArthur ordered him to
“将日本共产党中央委员会的全体成员从公共服务中清除和排除出去”
remove and exclude the full membership of the Central Committee of Japan's Communist Party from public service.
“赤色清洗”不再像1949年那样是一个心照不宣的优先事项
The Red Purge was no longer an unspoken priority like in 1949.
它现在已是官方政策
It was now official policy.
那些在1949年大规模裁员中未被悄然清除的人
Those not quietly purged in the 1949 mass layoffs
到了1950年则被迅速而公开地解雇了
were quickly and loudly fired by 1950,
这都得归功于松川事件
thanks to Matsukawa.
到1951年，当共产党人因其政治立场被清洗时
By 1951, as communists were being purged for their politics,
日本最近获释的战犯们却突然被“解除清洗”
Japan's recently freed war criminals were suddenly depurged,
被允许再次参与政治
permitted to participate in politics once more,
这是对麦克阿瑟战后最初步骤的黑暗而富有诗意的逆转
a darkly poetic reversal of MacArthur's first steps after the war
即释放政治犯和惩罚战犯
to free political prisoners and punish war criminals.
这些合作者之一是绪方竹虎
One of these collaborators was Ogata Takatora,
他是日本战时内阁的前高级情报官员，也是一名甲级战犯嫌疑人
a former top intelligence official in Japan's wartime cabinet and a suspected Class A war criminal.
被解除清洗后
After being depurged,
绪方立即重返政坛，作为吉田首相的自由党成员赢得了国会席位
Ogata dove right back into politics, winning a Diet seat as a member of Prime Minister Yoshida's Liberal Party,
这是日本的主要保守派政党
Japan's main conservative party.
他重返高位的速度很快
His return to high office was swift.
到1953年，也就是占领结束后的第二年，他已是副首相
By 1953, the year after the occupation's end, he was Deputy Prime Minister.
然而，美国在日本的反共战争并没有随着占领的结束而终结
Yet America's war against communism in Japan didn't end with the occupation.
它只是转入了地下
It just went underground.
这是一份1955年的中情局备忘录
This is a CIA memo from 1955,
记录了一名中情局官员与代号为POCAPON的线人之间的会面
documenting a meeting between a CIA officer and an asset codenamed POCAPON.
POCAPON的真实姓名，正是绪方竹虎
POCAPON's real name? Ogata Takatora.
没错，此时已是日本执政党领袖的绪方
That's right. Ogata, by now the leader of Japan's ruling political party,
竟然是中情局的线人，并且他带来了巨大的回报
was literally a CIA asset, and he delivered huge dividends.
在这次会面中，绪方向他的联络人提供了
In this meeting, Ogata's providing his handler information that only someone in his position
只有身处日本政治最高层的人才能提供的情报
at the highest level of Japanese politics could offer.
关于主要政治人物个性的信息，党内竞争的动态
Information about the personalities of leading politicians, the dynamics of inter-party rivalries,
以及关于日本两大保守党，自由党和民主党，合并提案的最新进展
and updates on a proposed merger between Japan's two largest conservative parties, the Liberals and the Democrats.
绪方向他的美国联络人保证
Ogata assures his American handler
旨在巩固一个单一反共保守党的合并已进入，引用其言，“最后阶段”
that the merger to consolidate a single anti-communist conservative party is in its, quote, final stages,
并提供了谈判细节，还预测他自己将成为这个新党的第一任首相
offers negotiation details, and predicts that he himself will become the first Prime Minister of this party.
然而，对中情局不幸的是，绪方于1956年意外去世
Unfortunately for the CIA, however, Ogata died, unexpectedly, in 1956.
对他们幸运的是，愿意拿中情局的钱来对抗共产主义的日本战犯名单还很长
Luckily, for them, the roster of Japanese war criminals, happy to take CIA money to combat communism, ran deep.
下一个登场的是岸信介
Next up to the plate was Kishi Nobosuke.
岸信介曾与儿玉誉士夫一同被囚禁
Kishi had been imprisoned with Kodama Yoshio,
他是一个特殊案例，因为作为1941年的内阁大臣
and he was a special case, because as a cabinet minister in 1941,
他确实签署了日本对美国的宣战书
he'd literally signed Japan's declaration of war against America.
然而，在这个反共主义者构建的奇异世界里，他不仅重返政坛
Yet, in this bizarro world the anti-communists built, he didn't just return to politics.
1957年，他还成为新合并的自由民主党的领袖
In 1957, he became the leader of the newly merged Liberal Democratic Party,
这使他成为美国在日本对抗共产主义最重要的盟友
making him America's most important ally against communism in Japan.
同年，他访问美国
That same year, he visited America
与艾森豪威尔总统打高尔夫球，并在洋基体育场投出第一球
to play golf with President Eisenhower and throw out the first pitch at Yankees Stadium.
我们无法确定岸信介本人是否是中情局的线人
We can't say for sure whether Kishi himself was a CIA asset,
主要是因为关于他的大量档案该机构至今仍拒绝公布
mainly because there are loads of files on him that the agency still refuses to release.
但我们确实知道，正是在岸信介担任自民党领袖和日本首相期间
But we do know that it was during Kishi's tenure as leader of the LDP and Prime Minister of Japan
该党及其候选人开始定期从中情局获得巨额资金
that the party and its candidates began regularly receiving huge payouts from the CIA.
在1950年代的剩余时间里以及整个1960年代
Tens of millions of dollars were given to the party
数千万美元被提供给该党，资助了他们在日本的权力崛起
over the remainder of the 1950s and throughout the 1960s, which funded their rise to power in Japan.
中情局与自民党合作的成功程度，怎么强调都不过分
It's hard to overstate just how successful this CIA-LDP collaboration was.
自该党成立以来的70年里，有65年都是它在执掌日本
In the 70 years since the party's founding, it's been in charge of Japan for 65.
但随着1950年代接近尾声，自民党将拥有何等主导地位尚不明确
But as the 1950s drew to a close, it wasn't yet clear just how dominant the LDP would be.
一方面，经济终于开始好转
On one hand, the economy was finally turning around.
另一方面，日本左翼似乎正在重振旗鼓
On the other hand, the Japanese left seemed to be getting their mojo back.
尽管共产党人因“赤色清洗”而被边缘化
Although the communists were sidelined by the Red Purge,
但日本社会党在1955年，58年和60年的选举中是一个有力的竞争者
the Japanese Socialist Party was a serious contender in the 1955, 58, and 60 elections.
正是这种来自社会党的威胁
It was this very socialist threat
促使中情局如此疯狂地支持和资助岸信介的自民党
that motivated the CIA to work so frantically to support and fund Kishi's LDP.
然而，这几乎适得其反
Yet that nearly backfired.
因为社会党受欢迎的一个重要原因在于
Because a big source of the Socialists' popularity was that,
尽管没人真正知道自民党和中情局之间发生了什么
even as nobody truly knew what was happening with the LDP and CIA,
但岸信介与美国关系极其密切已不是秘密
it wasn't a secret that Kishi was extremely buddy-buddy with America.
而到那时，许多日本人已经对被当作美国的小老弟感到有些厌倦了
And a lot of Japanese were, by this point, a little fed up with being treated like America's little brother.
这一切在1960年达到了顶点，这是塑造今日日本的又一个疯狂年份
This all reached ahead in 1960, another insane year that made Japan what it is today.
所以接下来请观看那个视频
So go watch that video next.
与此同时，1959年，日本最高法院准予松川事件被告重审
Meanwhile, in 1959, Japan's Supreme Court granted the Matsukawa defendants a retrial.
1963年，令日本社会震惊的是，所有被告的定罪都被推翻了
And in 1963, all of the defendants' convictions were, to the shock of Japanese society, overturned.
他们所有罪名均被宣告无罪
They were acquitted on all charges.
被告们依据麦克阿瑟宪法中保障的权利，随后起诉政府要求赔偿
The defendants, thanks to rights enshrined in MacArthur's Constitution, then sued the government for redress,
指控他们是应美国官员的要求而被故意陷害的
alleging they'd been intentionally framed at the behest of American officials.
然而，他们始终未能证明自己的指控
Yet they never were able to prove their case.
许多关于那一时期的政府文件至今仍被严格保密
Many government files on the period remain strictly classified.
因此，对于1949年困扰日本的深刻而致命的分裂
In turn, the Japanese people have been denied any real certainty about who was ultimately responsible
究竟谁应负最终责任，日本人民一直未能得到任何确切的答案
for the deep and fatal divisions that plagued Japan in 1949.
也正因此，今天的日本政治中仍然存在着某种悬而未决，甚至扭曲的东西
As such, there remains something unsettled, even warped, about Japanese politics today,
这要归因于这段动荡的时期，以及占领政策从理想主义的德谟克拉西建设
thanks to this turbulent period and the occupation's dramatic pivot away from idealistic democracy building
到犬儒主义的反共现实政治的戏剧性转变
to cynical anti-communist realpolitik.
这种转变，在某些方面，从一开始就内建于占领进程之中
This pivot was, in some ways, built into the occupation process from the start.
无论最初的占领及其产生的宪法具有何等积极，理想主义和德谟克拉西的精神
Regardless of the can-do, idealistic, and democratic spirit of the initial occupation and the constitution it produced,
它始终是一场占领
it remained an occupation.
日本德谟克拉西的需求总有与美国官员和国家安全的利益发生冲突的风险
There was always a risk that the needs of Japanese democracy would come into conflict with the interests,
无论是真实的利益，还是仅仅是感知到的利益
whether real or merely perceived, of American officials and national security.
这就是占领的本质
That's the nature of an occupation.
它不是一个德谟克拉西的过程
It's not a democratic process,
而是由一个有着自身图谋的外国政权自上而下强加的东西
but something imposed from above by a foreign regime with its own designs.
不过这并不是说，当我们审视现代日本历史的宏大画卷时
That isn't to say, when we look at the broad sweep of modern Japanese history,
占领完全没有达到麦克阿瑟所期望的一切
that the occupation fell short of everything MacArthur hoped for.
今日的日本是一个自由的德谟克拉西国家
Japan today is a liberal democracy.
松川事件的被告们得到了法庭审判的机会并最终被宣告无罪
The Matsukawa defendants received their day in court and were ultimately acquitted.
公民享有公民和政治权利，在公平选举中投票的自由
Citizens enjoy civil and political rights, freedom to vote in fair elections,
以及在市场经济中享有的高生活水平
and a high standard of living in a market economy.
但日本的政治仍然由单一政党主导
But Japan's politics remain dominated by a single party,
尽管它不受欢迎，尽管丑闻缠身
despite its unpopularity, despite many scandals.
或许是因为，在日本德谟克拉西文化的形成时期
Perhaps because, in the formative years of Japan's democratic culture,
它发育不良，因为美国的秘密行动有意扼杀了政治竞争
it was stunted, as clandestine American operations intentionally smothered political competition
并催生了一个对保密和腐败更为容忍的政权
and produced a regime more tolerant of secrecy and corruption
而不是容忍意识形态的多样性和分歧
than of ideological diversity and disagreement.
那些健康的德谟克拉西所必需的特质
Those essential qualities of a healthy democracy.
欲了解更多此类内容，请观看我们另外两个
For more like this, watch our two other videos
关于日本疯狂形成年代的视频，1932年和1960年
on Japan's insane formative years, 1932 and 1960,
依旧广告